MattRalston

blend of bioinformatics and biochemistry

contact

Matt Ralston 15 Innovation Way Newark, DE 19717

Phone: 302.547.2437 Email: mrals@udel.edu matthewralston.github.io LinkedIn:matthewralston

bioinformatics

Bowtie, Tophat, BWA Blast, Blat, Clustal Cufflinks, Trinity, Velvet Samtools, Picard, **Bedtools** DESeq, MACS, Circos

programming

♥ Ruby/Rails, R Bash, Python, Julia Matlab, LATEX, Racket MySQL, SQLite Javascript, CSS/HTML

laboratory

RNA-seg, gRT-PCR Northern & Western Spectrometry, HPLC Immunofluorescence Immunohistochemistry Microscopy, HPLC FACS, GC-MS Mammalian cell culture Anaerobic fermentation

summary

Combines an understanding of molecular mechanisms from a B.S. in Biochemistry with analytical strengths from an M.S. in Bioinformatics to produce and interpret 'omic datasets from Next Generation Sequencing (NGS) reflected by an academic research record. Enjoys research and development, from experimental design to analysis. Offers interdisciplinary expertise for teams of scientists, engineers, and analysts.

education

2012-2015 M.S. Bioinformatics and Computational Biology 3.97 University of Delaware

Thesis: Assembling Improved Gene Annotations in Clostridium acetobutylicum

with RNA Sequencing.

B.S. Biochemistry 2008-2012 University of Delaware

Minor in Biochemical Engineering; Research Fellowship; Merit Scholarships

experience

DELAWARE BIOTECHNOLOGY INSTITUTE 2012-Now

Newark, DE

Graduate Research Assistant

Accomplishments:

- Developed and utilized laboratory and computational workflows for first strand-specific deep RNA-seg and transcriptome assembly in *Clostridia*.
- Built and launched a genome browser for research community.

2010-2012 Center for Translational Cancer Research Newark, DE

Undergraduate Research Fellow

Investigated the BMP-signaling pathway in colon cancer cells and tissue.

leadership

2014 **Bioinformatic Student Association** Newark, DE

President

Organized and led a UNIX and HPC student development workshop.

2013 **IGERT Business, Ethics, and Communication Project**

Newark, DE

Project Manager

Won a proposal for a revision to Fraunhoffer CMB's vaccine production process.

publications

- "Complex and extensive post-transcriptional regulation revealed by integrative proteomic and transcriptomic analysis of metabolite stress response in Clostridium acetobutylicum", contributing author. BMC Genomics. (2015). Accepted
- "Overexpression of the L. plantarum peptidoglycan biosynthesis murA2 gene increases the tolerance of *E. coli* to alcohols and enhances ethanol production", contributing author. Applied Microbiology and Biotechnology 98.19 (2014): 8399-8411.
- "The Clostridium small RNome that response to stress: the paradigm and importance of toxic metabolite stress in C. acetobutylicum", contributing author. BMC Genomics. 14.1 (2013): 849.